<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
        <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
        <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
        <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
        <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
        ]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="exp" docName="draft-przygienda-lsr-ospf-security-states-00"
     ipr="trust200902" obsoletes=""
     submissionType="IETF" updates="" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="3" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true"
     version="3">
    <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.9.1 -->
    <front>
        <title abbrev="IGP Link/Node Security Advertisement">
            Advertising Link and Node Security Properties in OSPF/IS-IS
        </title>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-przygienda-lsr-ospf-security-states-00"/>
        <author fullname="Tony Przygienda" initials="A." surname="Przygienda" role="editor">
            <organization>Juniper</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1137 Innovation Way
                    </street>
                    <city>Sunnyvale</city>
                    <region>CA
                    </region>
                    <code/>
                    <country>USA
                    </country>
                </postal>
                <phone/>
                <email>prz@juniper.net
                </email>
                <uri/>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Acee Lindem" initials="A." surname="Lindem">
            <organization>LabN Networks, L.L.C.</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>301 Midenhall Way</street>
                    <city>Cary</city>
                    <region>NC
                    </region>
                    <code/>
                    <country>USA
                    </country>
                </postal>
                <phone/>
                <email>acee.ietf@gmail.com
                </email>
                <uri/>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Vinayaka Guntanakkala" initials="G." surname="Guntanakkala">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Juniper Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <country>India</country>
                </postal>
                <email>vinayakag@juniper.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date year="2023"/>
        <abstract>
            <t>
                This document defines a way for an Open Shortest Path First (OSPF)
                or IS-IS router to advertise different security states
                at node and/or link granularity. Such advertisements allow
                entities (e.g., centralized controllers) to determine whether a
                particular node/link or path meets security policies that have to
                be enforced. Here, the term "OSPF" means both OSPFv2 and OSPFv3.
            </t>
        </abstract>
        <note>
            <name>Requirements Language</name>
            <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
                "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
                14
                <xref target="RFC2119" format="default"/>
                <xref target="RFC8174" format="default"/>
                when, and only when, they appear in all
                capitals, as shown here.
            </t>
        </note>
    </front>
    <middle>

        <section toc="default" numbered="true">
            <name>Introduction</name>
            <t>OSPF/IS-IS, as an IGP, is one of the most critical protocols in a network and compromising integrity of
                any of its nodes by a misconfiguration or security attack can have catastrophic consequences. Though
                infrastructure can be deployed to monitor and alarm changes in security status of OSPF nodes it is
                desirable for a mechanism that allows fastest and completely non-ambigous detection of any
                security state change of OSPF nodes or links, independent of, e.g., status of a monitoring connection or
                implementation defect in any piece of the monitoring infrastructure or ultimately, successful attacks
                against such infrastructure. Link state database is in its nature ideally suited to carry such
                information given
                that it is not only a very fast mechanism due to the nature of flooding but also represents
                the ultimate source of truth in terms of topology state and thus security state.
            </t>
            <t>
                Security is not a single linear value but is rather most commonly expressed as a triad
                <xref target="CIA"/>
                of characteristics that are
                not necessarily related to each other in a specific technology. Hence we will use
                the same concept to redistribute a triad of sorted security property vectors for each characteristic
                (since we want
                to express strength of a certain technology to ascertain a characteristic unambiguously but we
                may be still interested whether a certain technology is deployed even if a "stronger" solution is
                already in place).
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="glossary" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Glossary</name>
            <t>
                The following terms are used in this document.
            </t>
            <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
                <dt>OSPF:</dt>
                <dd>
                    Open Shortest Path First
                </dd>
                <dt>IS-IS:</dt>
                <dd>
                    Intermediate System to Intermediate System
                </dd>
                <dt>LSA:</dt>
                <dd>
                    Link State Advertisement
                </dd>
                <dt>RI:</dt>
                <dd>
                    Router Information
                </dd>
                <dt>NSI:</dt>
                <dd>
                    Node Security Information
                </dd>
                <dt>LSI:</dt>
                <dd>
                    Link Security Information
                </dd>
                <dt>
                    sec-characteristic:
                </dt>
                <dd>
                    short notion for one of the CIA triad characteristics, i.e., confidentiality, integrity,
                    availability. We
                    will use C for a specific characteristic and |C for the set of all possible C values.
                </dd>

                <dt>sec-property:</dt>
                <dd>
                    single property of link or node for a C representing something like, .e.g., MACSEC with
                    key-id.
                    We denote a sec-property of a sec-characteristic as p_C and |P_C is the space of all possible p_C
                    values for a C.
                </dd>
                <dt>sec-property-vector:</dt>
                <dd>
                    sec-property-vector: is an ordered set of p_C \elem_of |P_C. We denote it as v_C.
                    (which implies basically that |P_C must be a total order).
                </dd>
                <dt>null:</dt>
                <dd>
                    element of |P_C for all C in |C that signifies security property that provides no security aspect.
                    Can be omitted,
                    i.e., is implicit. We will need that to compare sec-property-vectors of different lengths.
                </dd>
                <dt>null-vector:</dt>
                <dd>
                    sec-property-vector of length 0, i.e., no security property is present. It is implicit for a C in
                    case no v_C is present.
                </dd>
                <dt>|R_C:</dt>
                <dd>
                    |R_C is the space of all possible v_C.
                    Since p_C is a total order and v_C is an ordered set, |R_C is a total order.
                    We define the ordering relation later in the draft.
                </dd>
            </dl>
        </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>First Example</name>
            <t>
                Since the definitions are rather plentiful let us provide a first example. Assuming that we distribute
                for a given node A the following sec-property-vectors:

            </t>

            <table anchor="a-table" align="center">
                <name>Example Vector for A</name>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <th align="left">C</th>
                        <th align="left">v_C</th>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">Confidentiality</td>
                        <td align="left">[ mac-sec ]</td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">Availability</td>
                        <td align="left">[ 10% loss control traffic, 20% loss data traffic ]</td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">Integrity</td>
                        <td align="left">[ 5% ospf rx control traffic corruption, 10% other control traffic corruption,
                            20% corruption data traffic ]
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>

            <t>
                and in similar fashion for node B:
            </t>

            <table anchor="b-table" align="center">
                <name>Example Vector for B</name>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <th align="left">C</th>
                        <th align="left">v_C</th>
                    </tr>
                </thead>

                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">Confidentiality</td>
                        <td align="left">[ mac-sec, ospf-sha-3 ]</td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>

                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">Integrity</td>
                        <td align="left">[ 5% corruption data traffic ]</td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>

            <t>
                To disperse a first wrong assumption, we cannot decide which node is "more secure" since overall
                the security state is not an ordered space, only each of the sec-characteristics is. So we can only
                compare the sec-property-vectors for each sec-characteristic. Let us do that for each case.

            </t>

            <section numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Confidentiality</name>
                <t>
                    Node A advertises "mac-sec" as only sec-property here, while node B advertises "mac-sec" and
                    "ospf-sha-3".
                    Assuming "mac-sec" is a stronger security property than "ospf-sha-3" we can say that node B is more
                    secure since
                    we really compare [ mac-sec, null ] with [ mac-sec, ospf-sha-3 ] and the vectors being ordered the
                    first,
                    "strongest" elements are equal and the second element of the second vector is "stronger" than the
                    second element.
                    While it can be argued that mac-sec makes ospf-sha-3 redundant, we need to define a clear ordering
                    to allow
                    distributed computations and hence node B will be prefered.
                </t>

            </section>

            <section numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Availability</name>
                <t>
                    Node A advertises "10% loss control traffic" and "20% loss data traffic" while node B advertises
                    nothing.
                    Hence for node B the implicit vector [ null, null ] is used and we compare [ 10% loss control
                    traffic, 20% loss data traffic ].
                    Loss is a "negative" property and hence the lower the value the better. So node B is more secure
                    here.
                </t>

            </section>

            <section numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Integrity</name>
                <t>
                    Node A advertises "5% ospf rx control traffic corruption", "10% other control traffic corruption"
                    and "20% corruption data traffic"
                    as its vector while Node B advertises "5% corruption data traffic" which in reality will be
                    [ null, null, 5% corruption data traffic ] to make the vectors comparable via our definition.
                    Since null is better here than any corruption already the first element tells us that node B is
                    more secure in respect to integrity.
                </t>

            </section>


        </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Extensible Ordering Relation</name>
            <t>
                To provide a mechanism to compare sec-property to other sec-properties and possibly same
                sec-property with different values we define an extensible encoding of a sec-property.
                It will consist basically of the following fields:
            </t>

                <dl>
                    <dt>
                        sec-property-type:
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                        Value that identifies the specific property, e.g., ospf sha-2. Contrary to expectations,
                        this is not used except for informational purposes.
                    </dd>
                    <dt>
                        sec-property-strength:
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                        this defines the first part of the comparison relation. sec-property with higher strength is
                        considered "stronger" than sec-property with lower strength.

                    </dd>
                    <dt>
                        sec-property-attribute:
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                        this is a number which defines the second part of the comparison relation, e.g., key length
                        or percentage of corruption/loss. Whether the higher value is better or worse is defined
                        by flags. If a property encompasses multiple function the value has to encoded accordingly, i.e.,
                        if the algorithm and the key length are encoded in the same value, the value has to be
                        constructed e.g. in a way that the algorithm is encoded in the higher bits
                        and the key length in the lower bits
                        and the according value is comparable as a integer number.
                    </dd>
                    <dt>
                        sec-property-flags:
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                        the function of flags is to allow nodes that do not understand the semantics of the sec-property
                        to still be able to compare it correctly since we cannot exclude that new algorithms or even
                        completely new algorithms will be defined in the future. For the moment the only flag defined is
                        the indication whether the sec-property-attribute is a "negative" property, i.e.. the lower the
                        value
                        the better the property or vice versa or whether it should not be compared at all, i.e., ignored.

                    </dd>
                </dl>

            <t>
                This calls for another small example. Let us assume that somebody took a new codepoint for quantum
                encryption of a link and the strongest value today is 10. Of course the length of the quantum
                key plays a role and the longer the key the stronger the resulting security. So the encoding for
                a node not even aware such a thing exists would be:
            </t>
            <t>

                [ sec-property-type = ?, sec-property-strength = 11, sec-property-attribute [key length] = 2048,
                sec-property-flags = higher attribute is better ]

            </t>
            <t>
                which will allow a node that is not even aware what this sec-property means to compare and tie-break it
                correctly in a computation.
            </t>

            <t>
                A problem that remains with the value of the sec-property-attribute in case of implicit null
                sec-property. Unfortunately we have to assume that a implicit null for a "link loss" represents no losses
                and is therefore preferrable to any loss advertised by other nodes while it may simply mean that
                the information is not available. This is indicated by one of the flag values that provides information
                what the value in case of null element should be be.
            </t>

            <t>

            </t>
        </section>

        <section  anchor="encodings" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Encodings</name>

            <section anchor="node_sec" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Node Security Information Advertisement for OSPF</name>
                <t>
                    The Node Security Information TLV within the body of the OSPF RI Opaque LSA
                    <xref target="RFC7770" format="default"/>
                    is used to advertise current node security states.
                </t>

                <t>
                    This TLV is optional and is applicable to both OSPFv2 and OSPFv3.
                    The scope of the advertisement is specific to the deployment.
                </t>
                <t>
                    When multiple Node Security Information TLVs of the same type
                    are received from a given router, the
                    receiver MUST use the first occurrence of the TLV in the Router
                    Information (RI) LSA. If the Node Security Infomation TLV appears in multiple RI
                    LSAs that have different flooding scopes, the Node Security Information TLV in the RI
                    LSA with the area-scoped flooding scope MUST be used. If the Node
                    Security Information TLV appears in multiple RI LSAs that have the same flooding
                    scope, the Node Security Information TLV in the RI LSA with the numerically smallest
                    Instance ID MUST be used and other instances of the Node Security Information TLV MUST
                    be ignored. The RI LSA can be advertised at any of the defined
                    opaque flooding scopes (link, area, or Autonomous System (AS)). For
                    the purpose of Node Security Information TLV advertisement, area-scoped flooding is
                    RECOMMENDED.
                </t>

                <figure anchor="f1">
                    <name>Node Security Information TLV for OSPF</name>
                    <artwork align="left" alt="" name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |    Type                       |  Length                       |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |  Flags  |  Sec-Type           |           Sec-Strength        |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                          Sec-Attribute                        |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  | .. further elements of the vector ..                          |
    ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>where:</t>
                <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">

                    <dt>Type:</dt>
                    <dd>For OSPFv2, the Node security information is advertised as an optional
                        TLV of the OSPFv2 Router Information LSA as defined in section 2.1 of
                        <xref target="RFC7770" format="default"/>
                        and has a type of ?.

                        For OSPFv3, the Node security information is advertised as an optional
                        TLV of the OSPFv3 Router Information LSA as defined in section 2.2 of
                        <xref target="RFC7770" format="default"/>
                        and has a
                        type of ?.

                        The type indicates the according security characteristic, i.e., confidentiality, integrity,
                        availability.

                    </dd>
                    <dt>Length:</dt>
                    <dd>variable; same as defined in Section ?.</dd>
                    <dt>Value:</dt>
                    <dd>Vector of ordered sec-property elements.


                    </dd>

                </dl>

                <t>
                    Format of the vector:
                </t>

                    <dl>
                        <dt>
                            Flags:
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                            5 bit field that defines the semantics of the sec-property-attribute.
                            The first two bits indicate whether the sec-property-attribute
                            is a "negative" property, i.e., the lower the value the better the property or vice versa
                            or whether the sec-property-attribute should not be compared at all, i.e., ignored and is
                            carried only for information purposes. The third bit when set indicates that for
                            a null element the value of the property should be assumed as maximum (all ones) and when not
                            set as minimum (all zeroes) for comparison purposes.
                            The other bits are reserved and MUST be set to 0 on transmission and ignored on
                            reception.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>
                            Sec-Type:
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                            8 bit field that defines the sec-property-type which is not compared and only carried
                            for information purposes.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>
                            Sec-Strength:
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                            8 bit field that defines the sec-property-strength which is compared with higher value
                            indicating a stronger, i.e., "more secure" property.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>
                            Sec-Attribute:
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                            32 bit field that defines the sec-property-attribute which is compared according to the
                            flags.
                        </dd>
                    </dl>

                <t>
                    This TLV is optional and considered implicit null vector if not present for the according
                    characteristics. The scope of the advertisement is specific
                    to the deployment.
                </t>

            </section>

                <section>
                    <name>Node Security Information for IS-IS</name>

                <t>
                    The Node Security Information sub-TLV is defined within the body of the IS-IS Router
                    CAPABILITY TLV
                    <xref target="RFC7981" format="default"/>
                    to carry the Node security
                    Information available of the router originating the IS-IS Router CAPABILITY TLV.
                </t>

                <figure anchor="f2">
                    <name>Node Security Information Sub-TLV</name>
                    <artwork align="left" alt="" name="" type=""><![CDATA[
      0                   1
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |    Type       |   Length      |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |  Flags  |  Sec-Type           |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |    Sec-Strength               |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |      Sec-Attribute            |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     | .. further elements of the vector ..

    ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>where:</t>
                <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">

                    <dt>Type:</dt>
                    <dd>TBD</dd>
                    <dt>Length:</dt>
                    <dd>variable; same as defined in Section ?.</dd>
                    <dt>Value:</dt>
                    <dd>equivalent to OSPF with reduced field lenghts.
                    </dd>

                </dl>

            </section>


            <section anchor="link_sec" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Link Security Information Advertisement for OSPF</name>
                <t>
                    The Link Security Information sub-TLV is defined to carry the security state of the interface
                    associated with the link and has the same format as Node Security Information TLV with type reserved
                    as TDB while the security types are reserved from its own registry.
                </t>

                <t>

                    If this sub-TLV is advertised multiple times for the same link in
                    different OSPF Extended Link Opaque LSAs / E-Router-LSAs originated
                    by the same OSPF router, the sub-TLV in the OSPFv2 Extended Link
                    Opaque LSA with the smallest Opaque ID or in the OSPFv3 E-Router-LSA
                    with the smallest Link State ID MUST be used by receiving OSPF
                    routers. This situation SHOULD be logged as an error.
                </t>
                <t>
                    This sub-TLV is optional and indicates implicit null vector if not present. The scope of the advertisement is specific
                    to the deployment.
                </t>

            </section>
            <section>
                <name>Link Security Information Advertisement for IS-IS</name>
                <t>
                    The Link Security Information sub-TLV is defined to carry the security state of the interface
                    associated with the link and its format is equivalent to Node Security Information Sub-TLV
                    while the security types are reserved from its own registry.

                    The Link Security Information sub-TLV is defined for TLVs 22, 23, 25, 141, 222, and
                    223 to carry the Link Security Information of the interface associated with the link.
                </t>

                <section numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Procedures for Defining and Using Node and Link Security Information Advertisements</name>
                    <t>
                        When Link Security Information is present for a given Router, the value of the Link
                        Security Information MUST take precedence over the Node security information when considering
                        a link. In case a Link
                        Security_Information-Type is
                        not signaled, but the Node Security_Information-Type is, then the Node Security_Information-Type
                        value
                        MUST be considered to be the Security Information value for that link.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="APPS" toc="default" numbered="true"> <name>Deployment Considerations</name>
        <t>
            Although the advertisements provide a rich model of the current security state of the IGP (and
            possibly other applications on the node/link) it can be desirable to "squelch" all this
            information into a single comparable metric for computation purposes. Nothing prevents that.
        </t>
            <t>
                Given the fact that same sec-property-type can be advertised with different sec-property-strength
                a node MUST simply ignore such a scenario and use strength only. Obviously, as local policy,
                such a condition can be flagged and alarmed since it is expected that standardization of
                new sec-property-type will standardize its strength as well.
            </t>

            <t>
                Given the flags attached to the same value of sec-property-strength may differ across
                information provided by multiple nodes, such a condition leads to the vectors being
                basically incomparable, i.e. a sec-property-type like link loss cannot declare on one
                node that more loss is better while another node consider less loss better. This scenario
                leads unavoidably to byzantine security discussion and is kept out of scope of this
                draft.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="App" toc="default" numbered="true"> <name>Applications</name>
        <t>
          One possible, obvious application is to include nodes that meet security criteria in Flex Algorithm <xref target="RFC9350"/> or
          IP Flex Algorithm <xref target="I-D.ietf-lsr-ip-flexalgo" format="default"/> or use the information as a type of
            single or multi-dimensional metric.
        </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="IANA" toc="default" numbered="true">
            <name>IANA Considerations</name>
            <t>This document requests allocation for the following codepoints and registries.</t>
            <t>...</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Security Considerations</name>
            <t>
                Security concerns for OSPF are addressed in
                <xref target="RFC7474" format="default"/>,
                <xref target="RFC4552" format="default"/>, and
                <xref target="RFC7166" format="default"/>.
                Further security analysis for the OSPF protocol is done
                in
                <xref target="RFC6863" format="default"/>.
                Security considerations as specified by
                <xref target="RFC7770" format="default"/>,
                <xref target="RFC7684" format="default"/>, and
                <xref target="RFC8362" format="default"/>
                are applicable to this document.
            </t>

            <t>
                Implementations MUST ensure that malformed TLVs and sub-TLVs defined
                in this document are detected and do not provide a vulnerability for
                attackers to crash the OSPF router or routing process. Reception of
                malformed TLVs or sub-TLVs SHOULD be counted and/or logged for
                further analysis. Logging of malformed TLVs and sub-TLVs SHOULD be
                rate-limited to prevent a Denial-of-Service (DoS) attack (distributed
                or otherwise) from overloading the OSPF control plane.
            </t>

            <t>
                Advertisement of an incorrect security information may have negative
                consequences if e.g. actions like node sequestration are performed
                based on this information.
            </t>

            <t>
                There's no DoS risk specific to this extension, and it is not
                vulnerable to replay attacks.
            </t>

            <t>
                The presence of this information may also inform an attacker about
                vulnerable points in the network unless confidentiality along all
                flooding paths is provided.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Acknowledgements</name>
            <t>
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references>
            <name>References</name>
            <references>
                <name>Informative References</name>

                <reference anchor="CIA" target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0167-4048(03)00406-1.">
                    <front>
                        <title>A taxonomy for information security technologies</title>
                        <author initials="H.S" surname="Venter" fullname="H.S Bradner">
                            <organization/>
                        </author>
                        <date year="2003"/>

                    </front>
                    <seriesInfo name="Computer &amp; Security" value="22">
                    </seriesInfo>

                </reference>

            </references>
            <references>
                <name>Normative References</name>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7474.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4552.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7166.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6863.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7770.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7684.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8362.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7981.xml"/>

                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9350.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-lsr-ip-flexalgo.xml"/>
            </references>
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
